In the suttas it says that
to see pleasant feeling as painful,
which you
just discussed in detail right now.
But then it goes on to say
painful feeling as a dart,
>> Mhm.
>> and neutral feeling as impermanent.
>> So why not just painful feeling as
painful?
What's the aspect of
seeing it as a dart? >> So
pleasant feeling as unpleasant.
That's the first one, isn't it?
See pleasure as displeasure, displeasure
as a dart,
and neutral feeling
as impermanent.
Why would that be the Why do you need to
say
the prospect of a of of unpleasant
feeling should be seen as a dart?
should be seen as a dart?
Should be seen as even worse.
>> It's It's double painful.
>> Yeah. Yeah, that's kind of the what what
you're trying to
Well, to see, to convey.
Why is that?
Whom are you conveying it to?
Who are you seeing it for?
For whom are you rewriting
the context
of pleasant, unpleasant, neutral?
>> I mean, and obviously for the mind, like
for the animal, but I would say more
like experientially actually for the
tendency. >> Which is what the animal is for you
>> Which is what the animal is for you
there and then, exactly.
Yeah, so that's the point.
It's to regard it so that the animal will
to regard it so that the animal will
turn away from it.
You need to say regard it twice as much. Because see
Because see
like say and actually that's that's
probably something people can relate to.
Like um
Oh, I can handle
uh moderate amount of say central
engagement. Or acting out of ill will. I I can
Or acting out of ill will. I I can
handle it. I can handle what comes
after. I know it's going to be
uncomfortable, but I can handle it.
That means your animal will remain bound
by those feelings, by ignorance. Won't
be tamed.
So when you are practicing regarding of
say unpleasant feeling, prospect of an
unpleasant feeling as a dart
then you're increasing the value of woe.
You shouldn't be handling it to begin
with. Cuz it's a trap. It carries the danger.
Cuz it's a trap. It carries the danger.
Oh, I can handle a little bit of poison.
No. A gram of poison or a full glass,
it's equally deadly. That's the
perception you need to develop so that
the animal completely turns away cuz
anything less than that won't be
freedom.
So you're regarding the pain as twice as
bad so the things so that when things are
so the things so that when things are
not painful, the animal won't get
careless.
There'll be enough left in the bank of
that context to keep you on the right
track.
>> Okay, it's because they the usual
tendency towards painful feeling is to
either say I can handle it, doesn't
matter. It's just like no, you can't handle it.
It's just like no, you can't handle it.
You don't know how painful it will be,
one. >> Yes.
>> Yes.
>> As well with the dart, you might say you
don't know who's shooting it. He might
shoot it with incredible strength and it
just goes through you.
>> Yeah, all of the circumstantial
implications. Yeah, exactly.
But the point is that
the point is that
this whole practice of regarding is like
should apply to even the mere
possibility of it. It's not you're not
just waiting. You don't need to be
waiting for your pain to regard it as
as an arrow.
Just the mere prospect of things turning
painful if regarded as a dart, as an arrow
if regarded as a dart, as an arrow
means mind won't be careless in regard
to things that are not painful.
So you're as I said, you're inflating,
you're increasing the value
of staying on the right track.
Cuz otherwise, you won't.
If it were not necessary to be done
the Buddha wouldn't have said do it.
So again, it's not like on the level of
you need to
say irrationally start everything is
horrible. Everything is painful. No,
it's just a mere prospect of being
touched by pain
if the mind is not fully trained
you should regard it no, actually I
should I should not be in that position cuz
I should not be in that position cuz
that will be a dart. That will be a
deadly arrow.
So, what do you do now? Well, now,
because of that,
when the choice of sensuality present
itself, I say no, to protect myself from
the possible deadly arrow.
When the choice of ill will present
itself, I say no, again, to protect
myself from the deadly arrow.
So, I will be I will be giving zero
intentional basis
for the deadly arrow to land on me.
>> So, actually developing that perception
feeds into the first one as well. Seeing
>> Yeah, yeah, of course, of course, of
course, yeah. Yeah, exactly, exactly.
Then, the pleasant feeling
>> Yeah.
>> will be all
seen cautiously, seen as well, this is
unpleasant. If I have to be cautious
because it might be a trap, that's
already an unpleasant experience.
>> Mhm.
And then, impermanence for neutral
feeling, the possibility
of neutral feeling
to see that
as impermanent.
>> Mhm.
>> It's not just when painful feeling is
present, but also
>> Well, yeah, see, possibility
of a neutral feeling
>> Mhm.
>> would be like
the subtlest form of feeling.
Cuz obviously, the possibility of
discomfort is already uncomfortable on
some level.
>> Yeah.
>> The possibility of pleasure that you're
still deeming valuable, it's it's uh
it's kind of felt relating, pleasant on
some level.
>> Mhm.
>> But, the possibility of a neutral
feeling is already neutral.
is already neutral.
>> Mhm.
>> So, if you regard that as impermanent,
as unownable,
well, it means there's nothing else for
you to worry about. But, the thing is
it's not a practice that you could just
start off the
in the middle of everything.
It's the result. The result of training
rightly in regard to the pleasant
feelings, not falling for its hooks and
pressures. The result of training
rightly in the unpleasant feeling, not
losing sight and context and becoming
negligence. Then, you get to discern the
neutrality the the the feelings that basically in
the the the feelings that basically in
order to discern the neutral feeling as
the sutta says, you need to have
developed some wisdom.
>> Mhm.
>> Otherwise, it's just not seen, so it's
always going to be basically unpleasant
and so on.
And the wisdom is developed on a kind of
training rightly into the in regard to
the pleasure and displeasure.
>> Yeah.
>> So, it's kind of the subtlest part
whereby say you have already the mind is
already to a greater degree
to a greater degree
um tamed, contained through the right
context, regards some uh pleasure as a
trap, uncomfortable,
uncomfortable,
uh regards uh
pain as as as uh twice as painful
because if you lose the sight again, the
suffering will increase and so on. So,
then, yeah, say you developed in all of
that, >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> you could be on the level of oh, neither
pleasure nor displeasure. Oh, I regard
that as
as I said, a reason on its own,
impermanent. Its manifestation is the reason for
Its manifestation is the reason for
tending is the reason for its
impermanence, even if it still endures
here. I don't need to see it go away.
>> Mhm.
>> So, in other words, there will be no
asavas left anywhere to hide in regard
to this attitude towards pleasure or
that attitude towards pain or the
attitude towards the neutral feeling
that's kind of
not seeing it to the extent turning
away, looking past it and so on.
So, if you train rightly in regard to
the pleasure, you are training rightly
in regard to the pain.
You're training rightly in regard to
neutral feeling.
If you train rightly in regard to the
pain, you're training rightly in regard
to the other two.
So, it's it's like
different facets of the same principle
of training that as you train
in it
even more of it becomes discernable.
So, even subtler aspects of it become
more and more discernable cuz as I said,
you are actually training in it.
So, like when you say you are in a state
of neither pleasure nor displeasure,
just like sitting in your kuti for
example. I mean, you could say things are
I mean, you could say things are
neutral.
Objectively neutral.
Where is that feeling?
Let's put it that way.
Are you feeling it? Do you feeling it
like, "Oh, I am feeling this?"
Are you in it or is it in you? Or
what's your relationship with the
neutrality of that feeling?
>> That I would say the usual tendency is
to actually like go for I'm feeling it
rather than
it's arisen
>> Mhm.
>> by itself.
Or on its own.
So, actually not seeing that aspect of uncontrollability.
>> Well, that's the perception you could be
developing then.
Cuz that's See, the point is it's not
like you need to contrive or imagine a
neutral feeling. The point is you need
to build it up.
You build it up through not pursuing
pleasant feelings
and not
denying, resisting the unpleasant
feelings. You build it up by rightly
training in regard to those palpable
feelings.
And then in solitude and so on when
you're left with neutral feeling,
again, that's where you could start now,
okay, I could see this thing as there.
It's there. Being felt.
Being felt.
Not necessarily see myself feeling it or
in it or comes from me and relate myself
personally to it, so to speak.
And yeah, I mean, those perceptions are
doable, but
and people can, as I said, even wrap
their head around even
even before they're able to do them and
then think they're doing them because
they make sense.
But what I'm saying is you don't want to
be doing it
on the basis of an imaginary neutral
feeling. You want to actually be feeling a
You want to actually be feeling a
neutral, neither pleasant nor
unpleasant, and then seeing that thing
really as such.
Not coming from me for not in relation
to me, just there, first and foremost.
Then I choose to relate to this or this
or that, but first and foremost is just
felt enduring on its own. I'm not trying
to change it, I'm not trying to
understand it, I'm not trying to get
into it. Just trying to see it for what
it is while it's there to the extent
that it is.
And see that's already like what we
spoke before that
whole development of like peripheral
awareness of indirectly attending cuz
you can't directly attend
well actually to any of your feelings to
be but when it comes to the neutral
feeling reason on its own on account of rightly
reason on its own on account of rightly
training in regard to the pleasant and
unpleasant feeling through right virtue,
right restraint and so on.
That feeling is even subtler
peripherally. So if you're expecting to see it as a as
So if you're expecting to see it as a as
a thing that can be directly attended
and measured through your perception, it
you know when you're seeing it
correctly. You will be imagining it.
So that's like you you don't you don't
force it or rush it as to okay, I must
present these perceptions and you got
the neutral feelings like no, no.
Are things either pleasant or unpleasant
now? Let me learn how to discern that as
Let me learn how to discern that as
something that's already being felt
while I'm discerning it.
Cuz you want to feel it but you don't
want to be doing the feeling
so to speak.
Cuz it's already felt. So you want to
discern that which is already felt as
such. Not like oh, I want to feel it as such
Not like oh, I want to feel it as such
because that's what I learned.
That's why again the whole training in
virtue and guiding of the sense those
has to be developed beforehand because
if those coarse modes of interfering
are not tamed and subdued, you're not
going to be able to stay on the level of
not forcing the feeling of that which is
already you'll be doing it.
You'll be falling for it.
So, what you know,
you look back, step back, look at the
the the entirety of your currently
enduring situation.
If it's felt pleasantly, it's fine.
You're not trying to change it. If it's
felt unpleasantly, you're not trying to
If it's felt neither pleasant or
unpleasant, you're not trying to change
that either.
So, that's the first and foremost say
uh training for somebody that is living
according to the virtue syllabus and
guarding of the sense doors.
So, it's like, let me peripherally not
lose the sight of an enduring feeling
for as long as it endures, really.
And it doesn't matter why or how it came
about. So, don't fall into rationalizing
it. Oh, it's because of it doesn't
really matter. It's completely relevant.
And as a matter of fact, yeah, the
suttas even say that. Like, the feelings
can be born out of what? 78 reasons.
Change of the elements, earth, water,
fire, air. And then one of them is like
circumstance, accident. Then another one
is previous karma.
Either way,
feeling is there and the training is the
same. Like, no matter why.
So, that's that's another way of staying
with a feeling correctly would be
say you're say building up the right
environment, right restraint, you're in
seclusion, and like, I don't know,
feeling of displeasure is present.
And then you see your mind wanting to
rationalize and explain it. And it's
like, oh, I'll actually I won't fuel
that. Although if it feels like it will offer
Although if it feels like it will offer
a solution, no, I'm not actually
fighting for this reason why the
feelings came about.
Instead, I want to train
my relationship in regard to the any
feeling that can come up on account of
anything. Then,
there will be no more problems for me.
Because if any feeling whatsoever can be
rightly contained, not acted out of,
it doesn't matter if it's the previous
karma, other people, or circumstances
inflicting it upon you, you will be
untouched. And that's the sole reason
you were concerned with rationalization
to begin with is cuz you were touched by
it.
>> So, in that sense, see all three
feelings as impermanent.
>> Well, yeah, obviously. Fundamentally,
you would be surmounting the whole
domain of feelings, and there will be
nothing felt
as the sutta says for an arahant.
In other words, no arising arisen
feeling can touch him.
Touch the citta.
>> I never thought about that sutta in that
progressive way.
And like the with the three feelings,
see that as painful as a dot.
>> Or relatively progressive way.
>> Yeah.
>> As I said, it's like
Yeah. I'm saying that these facets, they
can be developed,
will become
more and more apparent, more easily
accessible as you start to develop it.
So, then yes, you would see there is
like a progression.
But it's really practice of the same
principle. So, if you train in regard to the say
So, if you train in regard to the say
say no to the coarse sensuality and
restraining yourself and enduring the
feelings that come on account with, you
are training in regard to all the
feelings. You won't be able to see the
subtlety of the neutral feeling and
right attitude, but it's already
included in that development, and it
will lead to
revelation of the those other facets
that you've been carrying
through practicing rightly on this
coarse level to begin with.
So, in that sense, yes, cuz there will
be more
clearer facet revealed later on, facets.
That's like in that sense, it's
progressive kind of progressing
practice, but it's not like one leads to
two and three.
Like by doing one, you are getting two
and three, and then two becomes
apparent. By doing one and two, you're
getting three, and then one, two, three
become apparent. By doing three, you're
getting one and two.
And obviously, like any principle of
right sati,
say, correctly practiced recollection of the
correctly practiced recollection of the
right context,
is the principle of training the animal
rightly. You know, whether you're recollecting,
You know, whether you're recollecting,
oh, what's what's the current what's my
current mood? What's my current What's
the current state of the animal? Is it
elated or depressed? Or whether you're
asking yourself, what's the current
enduring feeling?
You're basically addressing the same
thing. That's why four satipatthana
leads to the one way purification of
being from all the asavas.
Uh because, you know, sometimes, like
asking about the animal, thinking about
the animal, might just become too
abstract or or just like flat.
But there is a current enduring feeling.
So, how about
you reveal that through your
recollection? Again, not for the sake of
Again, not for the sake of
finding
an answer or some revelation behind it,
but for the sake of uncovering it for as
long as it's there.
And you uncover it, as we said before,
through right questioning, whereby it's
discerned as a thing that's already
part of your situation, not as a thing
that's you are directly attending and
merging and working with or something.
It's like, no, no, no. You just want to
like recall it without directly
attending to it.
So, how am I currently feeling while I'm
sitting here doing talking? That's what
you want to know. Okay, that's the
currently during feeling while I
continue sitting in seclusion, walking, or
sitting in seclusion, walking, or
whatever.
Um and see
how long, how far, how clearly can you
see it indirectly enduring while being
felt.
How subtly can you perceive? How far can
you see it without moving your eyes to
look for it?
And that's kind of the point of the
training because
for as long as your understanding
and clear seeing depend on your
attention, means they're conditioned, which means
means they're conditioned, which means
when your attention changes,
your wisdom goes away with it.
But if now you're seeing things without
looking at them and can see things
without needing to attend to them
directly, they always there.
they always there.
Whatever you attend, whatever distracts,
whatever sense comes up occupies your
mind, the framework will remain unchanged. The
the framework will remain unchanged. The
truth will remain the same, to put it
that way.
And there was that um
What was it? That Tedi Gata, I think.
I think it was that nun
that used to be like a courtesan. Mhm.
Or something. And there's this whole
like lots of verses. They're like, I
don't know.
10, maybe more. Kind of like a long
poem. >> Oh, yeah.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> That ends every section ends but the
uh the um
Well, actually I remember it in Serbian.
How was it in English?
Kind of something like poetically
equivalent of but the face of truth
hasn't changed.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh and
that was how every kind of refrain would
end. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> And before that she would describe how
basically cuz she's like 80 years old
now, everything changed. She used to
have the beautiful hair.
>> Mhm.
>> Seduce people. Now it's like wrinkled,
gray, falling off. But the truth
remained the same from back then when
she understood the Dhamma. Everything
else that deteriorated came, went, uh
all of that, the truth, the frame, the
recognition, the understanding of that
was not dependent on any of those
things. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> On any of those activities, any of those
engagement engagements, any of those
actions, or
or say um
uh uh
conditioned kind of um being held up by
your determination or interest and so
on. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> Um the truth remain unaffected by that.
And as these changes occurred, the truth
remain unchanged. Like her mind hasn't
changed cuz it's been tamed and
understood independent of whether you're looking at
independent of whether you're looking at
it directly, whether your attention,
whether with cues, whether with prompts.
No, it was seen.
The internal eye has been trained
sufficiently enough to see it to a
sufficient extent whereby you would see
it without looking at it.
And that's why Dhamma is referred to as
the internal eye that begins with
sotapatti.
>> I like
>> Yeah, internal eye. Yeah, the eye that
sees. But it's not the actual eye that
sees. So, sights, sounds, smells, tastes,
So, sights, sounds, smells, tastes,
touches, mano eye, attention,
manasikara, literally,
are things bound with the directionality
of the six senses. The Dhamma eye is
independent of all the six senses.
So, it sees without looking through
eyes, nose,
including your manasikara. It sees
without manasikara. Doesn't need
manasikara to see things. Doesn't need
things to be attended in order to be
recognized, discerned,
revealed, known, understood.
And that's the yoniso part of
manasikara, but now we're getting
technical. >> They're not A.
>> They're not A.
>> The Yeah, they're not AOA, yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
So, that's why again, like I'm
I'm just so vehemently and consistently
against any method because any method is
bound cannot not be connected with ways
of attending and hearing, doing, and
fabricating. It's like it's completely
taking you the other way.
The more you think that's what the
Dhamma is, the further away from the
Dhamma you
you travel.
And then, management versus uprooting.
Again, the same principle.
If your view is about uprooting, well,
you'll never go too far. Even when you
get caught in management or attending
and shifting,
but uprooting should be independent of
all these acts, all these sankharas,
basically. Asankhata Dhamma, the undetermined.
Asankhata Dhamma, the undetermined.
The unattended, the unman- the unborn,
the unmanifested, you know, the
mystified suttas. No, that's exactly
what it means.
Seen without a need for a direct look.
And because there is such a thing that
can be seen without looking,
that's why Nibbana and the holy life is
possible, as the Buddha said. If it
weren't unborn, unmanifested, un-this,
un-that, the whole life wouldn't be possible.
the whole life wouldn't be possible.
So, if there would be no thing that you
could see without looking through six
senses, then yes, freedom from suffering would
then yes, freedom from suffering would
not be possible. But, because there is
such a thing
that you don't need six senses to see
and discern and cultivate and understand
and develop, then freedom from suffering
is possible.
But, obviously it's a lot more
nice to regard it as a mystical entity
of the unborn, the unmanifested.
The truth, the hidden truth behind the
reality of appearances and stuff like
that. It's like, no, it's simply the not
A of A.
Seen to the indirect extent without
making it into either A or B.
Seeing the middle way between A and B,
the middle ground.
Without denying A completely till it
becomes another thing
or without distracting yourself
away from it till it becomes another
thing.
And you're closer to the non-A, non-A,
you're closer to the unborn,
unmanifested, you're closer to Nirvana
by prac- by training in virtue,
by guarding of the sense doors, by not
trying to get rid of the unpleasant
things at all by any means necessary.
You are actually
uncovering that middle ground
that middle ground
that you can eventually understand and
discern without a need of looking at it
without a need of looking at it
directly.
Cuz if you do,
it's not that thing anymore.
Although on paper, oh, it's the same
thing
that I'm looking at. The fact that
you're looking at directly, it's not the
peripheral phenomena that you need to
discern. >> So, not a word to be another word for
>> So, not a word to be another word for
peripheral.
>> Yeah, exactly.
So, not a word to be an empty village or
everything else we talked about that the
suttas describe the sense bases. They do
not appear directly.
But it is real as such, that's the
point. That's the same like
questioning like what is a currently
doing feeling, but you don't want to be
directly looking at it.
You want to learn and develop that
ability to see it
to see it
indirectly.
Like I'm as I said, because it's there
in that indirect manner. Your body is
there in an indirect manner. Your
feelings are there in an indirect
manner. Your citta is there in an
indirect manner. Those are the only
means you can access them correctly.
If you're thinking you're doing
kayasatti correctly by attending to it
through your sensations, that's not the
kaya. That's not the internal body.
That's not the what the body is. That's
like your ideas and perceptions,
secondary perceptions of it.
So, body, feelings,
citta, and the the dhammas, the thoughts
as a phenomena present themselves, those
things can only be known, discerned,
fully understood, contemplated
indirectly. Only dhamma I can see them correctly.
Only dhamma I can see them correctly.
Otherwise, they won't be those things.
So, say you discern a unpleasant feeling
peripherally, but you don't fall into a trap of acting
but you don't fall into a trap of acting
out, rationalizing it,
or trying to like really attend to it
directly so to solve it, you leave it
peripheral, but you don't completely
ignore it either.
That's that development of
of the the dhamma, even if you don't
necessarily still recognize it for what
it is.
And see like it's impossible that
somebody would do this by chance.
It's impossible that somebody would
for no
it without any external instruction or
somebody telling them
and insisting that no, no, you got to
stay on that level. Don't make it into a
new thing, but don't completely ignore
it either.
Unless somebody has learned enough to
actually start gauging that balance
through that external help, nobody will
ever do it. Why? Because say you start
you ask yourself, "How am I feeling?"
Well, I feel a bit unpleasant.
And now I look at that feeling directly.
Oh, I'm feeling unpleasant. In my mind,
it's the same feeling.
And in a way it is the same feeling, but
it's not
there is a difference between whether
that same feeling
is seen peripherally or is attended
directly.
And that difference is not something you
can see for yourself.
If you see that for yourself without
external guidance, you'll become
sammasambuddha.
So, the external guidance outlines that
for you. The training they will they
will they will eventually reveal the
distinction between the seemingly same thing
between the seemingly same thing
being actually seen indirectly, it's one
thing, or directly, it's another thing.
And that's the fundamental difference
between internal and external in the suttas,
internal and external in the suttas,
including Satipatthana.
Seeing indirectly, seen peripherally
without making it into a directly
attended thing is what the domain of
internal is.
Seeing it directly
directly attending to it is what the
domain of external is.
When you fully train in regard to domain
internal in regard to the domain of the internal,
in regard to the domain of the internal,
then internal and external will become
clear. They won't be conflated. They won't be
They won't be conflated. They won't be
confused.
And the more you train in regard to the
domain of the internal for what it is
you realize
it's kind of ceasing to be mine.
Ceasing to be internal.
That's it for the arahant. It's just
things left there, so to speak.
He can still recognize them between like
externally external and slightly less
external. But fundamental because
But fundamental because
the internal dimension, the peripheral
not being seen, not being developed,
that's where the sense of atta is,
that's where the appropriation is,
that's where the asavas are. Everything
is in that level that's neither here nor
there. Neither quite in the level of A
nor quite on the level of B.
It's always in relation to things.
And that's why it's compared to a fire
in the suttas. Like it takes up the
fuel, but it's not the fuel.
So upadana
it's not the five aggregates, cannot be
found in any of the five aggregates
whichever way you attend them
but it it it does not exist anywhere
apart from them.
So it's in a relation to them. It's the
not A of the A of the aggregates, A B C
D.
And it remains not seen cuz all people
can see is A B C D E F G and so on.
They don't look for the relationship
that's half revealed when they attend A.
For relationship that's half revealed
when they attend to the B and so on.
So, currently during feeling is
unpleasant. Seeing it like that indirectly
Seeing it like that indirectly
is
Well, you could even regard it it's it's
like a it's it's one feeling, one type.
Directly attending to it although it
looks the same, feels the same
it's a different thing.
So, now if you directly attend to that
feeling you need to discern
the peripheral to that newly directly
attended feeling.
You need to learn how to see it, feel it
peripherally without directly attending
to it.
That's what you're going to be talking
about two points of view at once.
>> Mhm.
When you speak about
being simultaneously
>> Yes.
>> present.
>> Yes, exactly.
Cuz it's not like that you're
denying the external, the directly attended
the external, the directly attended
thing when you're discerning the
peripheral. No, you're just revealing
both at the same time.
But again, peripheral is always indirect
and that's how you need to train it and
train yourself in seeing it.
Any tendency to make it
a direct thing that you can now
rationalize, think about, proliferate
further Well, you got to restrain it. You can't
Well, you got to restrain it. You can't
completely stop it, but you need to
recognize that when you catch yourself
in doing it
instead of denying it and oh, let me go
back to the beginning. No, no, no.
Discern the peripheral in regard to
that.
>> Yeah, I was think like the the
what you said that then basically the
whole like especially
like especially
like in the beginning it's all about
not really changing the direction but
undoing the just tendency of always
directly attending and you kind of
undirecting. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
Well, undoing the tendency of directly
attending only to the extent necessary
to reveal the implicit peripheral of
whatever is directly attended.
Not like to completely cuz you can't.
You cannot have attention. You're not be
attending to something.
So that's why again the whole virtue and
sense restraint
it's it's like
well, it's obviously not negotiable but
it's like part of the training cuz
that's how you begin.
Cuz the
uh
virtuous things, non-desire,
uh wholesome things are the things
that yes, you're still fully directly
attending without any
recognition of the implicit
simultaneously enduring indirect
peripheral determined by it,
but they carry the possibility to see
it. The unwholesome things as I said
before, they remove that possibility. They're
they remove that possibility. They're
too far down the line towards the
perversion of the unwholesome
that anything peripheral you're
discerning will be tainted by it. Won't
be the peripheral.
So that's why I mean like you're closer
to the rightly
>> Yeah.
>> discerning Nibana simply through
guarding your your your your sense doors
even without any knowledge or
understanding yet.
So yeah, whether you're sitting,
walking, talking, eating, working,
corner of your eye, back of your mind,
to that extent at the back of your mind.
Don't stop in order to really dig in
there cuz it won't be there you're
digging. Just
Just
discern what is the currently enduring
feeling.
What's the currently enduring flavor of
that situation?
What's the currently enduring body
posture? Again,
it's on that level. I'm not stopping
everything to directly attend the fact
that I'm seated. No, I wouldn't know
that. I uncovered that knowledge without the
I uncovered that knowledge without the
making it into a new directly attended
thing. And let it endure.
And let it endure.
Protect it.
And that's already taming the animal,
taming the cheetah.
Cuz you do that long enough, you won't
have to
um be
peripherally discerning your enduring
feeling or mood or body posture to reveal the
or mood or body posture to reveal the
cheetah. You could just peripherally
discern the cheetah. You would have seen
enough signs of the mind to see the mind
for what it is,
which is an always indirect thing.
That's why it's invisible in the
beginning for people if they were not
virtuous, celebrate, withdrawn from
sensuality, withdrawn from the company of lust,
withdrawn from the company of lust,
aversion, distraction,
dwelling in seclusion, seeing the signs
of the mind, it's not possible as the
sutra says.
You're still too close.
Kind of.
Yeah, it's more like you you have
you still do not possess
um the capable lens that can
focus on the
right level between here and infinity.
>> Focus on the right level between here
and infinity.
>> Yeah.
Yeah, cuz you know like the lens, you
could like focus close up or go into
infinity. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> There's nothing in between. So, you
imagine just like a it's either focus
here or there.
>> Yeah.
>> Stuff in between exists, but it's all
blur. Can't be seen. So,
So,
training in virtue, training in
restraint, training in the precept, it's
basically training how to discern that
which is in between, that which is as I
said, always indirect, always
peripheral, always there, felt enduring
in a certain situation
without making it
into a thing that I'm preoccupied with,
indirectly kind of engaging with or
attending it.
That's why this self-questioning and
recollection in that manner, that's
basically the only method that you could
say cuz it's not really a method. It's
not something you can just mindlessly
uh do or repeat.
But through questioning, you kind of
hint at that
>> Mhm.
>> without seeking necessarily, "Okay, this
is what it is, the answer." or
something. You're just like, "How am I
feeling?" So, it's not like finding the
right answer to the question. There
isn't one. The question is, "How am I
feeling? >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> What am I doing?
>> What is my current body posture? Again,
you don't need to stop sitting,
talking in order to find the answer that
you were sitting and talking.
>> Mhm.
>> It's already seen.
Leave it on that level and discern it
and curve the tendency to or let me make
it into a more palpable thing that I can
work with. That's you falling into the
trap of over-attending it.
>> Mhm.
>> So, that's the right tuning and so on.
Too much effort, too little effort.
What is the currently during mood? Just
the overall.
Do you feel up or down, heavy or light,
inspired or depressed?
You already know that.
Even the even the most sutra person and
then read no sutras or anything
would be able to give you an answer to
this. If you ask them to explain it,
they would fall into some
external psychologization,
rationalization through whatever kind of
concoction of
modern science / medicine views, ideas
of consciousness or whatever to explain
it. It's going to be nonsense,
obviously, but
first and foremost, they would tell you
how they feel. They would tell you what
mood they are in.
They just won't be able to stay on that
phenomenological level
without making it into something that it
isn't.
>> So, when we
when we ask those questions, it's more
about when you say as well let the
question endure like don't jump for an
answer. >> Exactly.
>> Exactly.
Cuz you're not looking for an answer.
You're looking for uncovering of what's
already there, which, as I said
accidentally, is the right answer. But
not if you answer it.
>> And it's in a way it's as well getting
to know the process of how you attempt
to answer it.
>> Yeah, it's more like about curbing it.
See like cuz you can see how people
would fall into then
well, they wouldn't be able to stay on
that level. They would either be
not asking the question.
It's just everything is like
self-evident. Whatever I can observe and
measure, which is, you know, the vast majority
which is, you know, the vast majority
of, say,
commentarily oriented Buddhists cuz
often you hear that like oh, modern
science and Buddhism are saying the same
thing. Everything is measurable,
predefined. There are factors, there are results,
There are factors, there are results,
and it's all like, you know, moment A,
moment B, to C.
Um so, that's like one extreme
in terms of the views, but then you have
another extreme where they would ask the
question, but then mystify the question.
Say, there is no answer.
>> Mhm.
>> It's like, well, no. You got to find the
middle ground. So, you do you are
seeking the answer, just not on your own
terms. But see, when you tell people, well, you
But see, when you tell people, well, you
can't just answer it
cuz you will fall into a trap of that
material material materialist view,
the commentarial view,
then they go the other way, and then
they say, well, there's no answer.
Then you just ask the question, and
whatever space opens up becomes their
answer, becomes overly attended thing.
That they think it's a non-answer cuz
they abstain from the answer. Cuz often
you hear that from
kind of Advaita Buddhists, how I call
them. They would often tend to like um
They would often tend to like um
uh
you know, they would say things like,
don't hold to fixed views.
And completely oblivious to the fact
that that is their fixed view.
That they very much hold on to.
Or it's like, abstain from any judgment.
Well, ease your form of judgment.
So, it's not as easy as to just abstain
from answering
to to to find that middle ground. No.
Abstaining from answering will become
your your form of answer.
Why? Because again, you're overly
attending it. You don't know how not to
make it into a thing.
So, that's why it's like, yes, it's
correct. Ask a question.
Don't seek an answer, but it doesn't
mean, oh, and be open to whatever
universe reveals to you. No, no. You do
need to find the answer.
It just can't be you who is providing
the answer.
So, ask the question looking for an
answer, but abstain from answering it,
but remain looking for an answer.
That's how you get the right balance.
>> Yeah, don't abandon the questioning.
>> Exactly. And don't abandon the the
implication of the question.
There is an answer there. You need to
discern it.
If you dismiss it and become like a like
a universe-worshipping mystic,
the periphery remains hidden, remains
covered. The middle ground, middle way
remains obscured.
If you just answer it because, you know,
quote the Abhidhamma, that answers
everything, as as moving systems and parts,
as as moving systems and parts,
everything fits and explains, again, you
obscured the fact that there is an
answer that wasn't on your own terms.
Even if you stated the right thing,
but you stated it as an answer, as
something that you directly attended,
it's not that peripheral thing that's
being felt.
So, that dimension remains obscured for
as long as you're rushing in with your
answers.
That's why it's like it's
incomprehensible for people that
approach the suttas with that kind of,
as I said, scientific everything is
explainable. It's the five factors and
the four this
the seven steps lead to the eight and
three and two. You know, people back in
the day used that simply to remember, to
help like cultivate the the transmission
memory, but now today they became
like a factual listings.
So, from that point of view, well, there
is nothing else to do in the suttas. You
just got to
learn and internalize the ideas of these
lists, and that's it. Every cuz they're
there to explain,
not to lead onwards, as as the suttas
would say.
But if information is not leading you
onwards to see it for yourself, it's not
the Dhamma. Even if it's the right thing
repeated on the paper.
And that's a thing that Nyanavira said
when that logician, I think, some
that logician, I think, some
mathematician logician was presented the
suttas and he read it like, "Well, this
is mere tautology."
Cuz he couldn't see there's anything to
develop because it's he approached it as
a as a as a statement of facts.
So, it when you know, when the Buddha
says the one who doesn't act
you know, out of their desire, the
desire diminishes. It's like, "Oh, yeah,
well, that's just a statement of fact. I
already know that."
In other words, I already have an
information. But one thing is to have an information,
But one thing is to have an information,
another thing is to recognize, "No, no,
no, there has to be training implicit in
this." Behavior that
Behavior that
that actually guides in that direction
whereby these things are seen and then
the dimension becomes
the dimension of the indirect feeling,
the indirect body, and so on become
revealed.
Without it, as I said, you will be
thinking it and you will be thinking
that you are thinking it,
but it won't be it.
The middle way won't exist for as long
as that
uh the signs of the minds that that that
the indirect is not seen to the
sufficient extent.
That's why again, the entire noble
eightfold path
rests upon
the right view, the noble view, the
noble internal dhamma eye.
Without it, there is no noble eightfold
path. Even if you make perfect sense out
of it and everything fits,
you are not seeing it for yourself.
So, seeing that indirect without
directly looking at it is what it means
seeing things for yourself.
Cuz nobody can come in between that. No
circumstance, no chance, no sense, it's not dependent
no chance, no sense, it's not dependent
on the sense objects. It's just
between you and your point of view
pretty much.
Even Mara can come in between that.
As the suttas tell us. So the
So the
mystical side and the scientific
Obviously they're both
both bees.
Yeah. Are they Would you Would you say
that is a kind of
all-encompassing dichotomy of Like um
>> Yeah, it's like all of the views,
whatever permutations of the individual
combinations, would boil down to these two basically.
would boil down to these two basically.
Either you'll be leaning on the
explanatory side or on the side that
dismisses the implication of the question and just
the implication of the question and just
starts to glorify the question in and of
itself. Yeah.
>> When you said that um
like it was in the context of pleasant,
unpleasant, and neutral feeling.
>> Mhm.
>> And you were saying that the neutral
feeling is
more quote-unquote in the peripheral than the
quote-unquote in the peripheral than the
other two.
>> Well
No, they're all the peripheral whenever
they're felt, but it's more like
>> It's more subtle, you think?
>> It's the subtlest to discern. It's the
hardest to discern correctly as a
phenomenon without overdoing it or underdoing it,
without overdoing it or underdoing it,
so to speak.
>> Cuz when when you said it for whatever
reason, I thought like, yeah, how do I
usually I mean, what do I associate with
Like with pleasant and painful feeling,
there is usually a certain
>> Well, see even the suttas describe it.
They don't call it neutral.
>> Neither.
>> They call it neither pleasant or
unpleasant. Or neither unpleasant nor pleasant.
Or neither unpleasant nor pleasant.
So it's the absence of the two that
reveals it. So you see, it's like a
twice as indirect, so to speak.
>> Yeah.
>> Pleasure and pain are already indirect.
Like feeling is already indirect to
whatever you're directly perceiving.
It's already the nature of feeling
already means a different
less direct direction of your
perception. Put it that way.
Put it that way.
But it's the absence of pleasure or pain
when you know that it's that's what's
felt, that's how you discern the
neutral. So it's like indirectly
indirect.
>> So the neutral feeling is
um
>> It's defined by not being neither
pleasant nor unpleasant.
>> By by absence of pleasure and pain,
exactly. Simultaneously enduring absence of
Simultaneously enduring absence of
pleasure and pain.
>> Yeah, because the other ones had when I
thought about they had a they have a
certain fullness.
fullness.
>> Yeah, exactly. They're a bit more
palpable. Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
That's why the neutral feeling is most
of the time not seen, not known, which
is why it's felt unpleasantly.